All right, we're going to start. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף
daf is
פ"ה. Peh Hei. Is that right? No, it's פ"ד, Peh Daled, excuse
me. And we start, thank you very much, we start five lines
from the top, אי הכי ee hachi on פ"ד עמוד א, Peh
Daled Amud Aleph, and basically the entire day-to-day is going to be
working out the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel where the
גמרא Gemara said yesterday that if two חצרות chatzers have equal access,
equally easy access, לזה בפתח ולזה בפתח lazeh bapetah u'lazeh bapetah to
something, then it is forbidden on both חצרות. chatzers. It is considered
both of their רשויות reshuts and they're competing, and if they didn't
make an עירוב. eruv. Or if they both have equally difficult access,
לזה בזריקה ולזה בזריקה, lazeh bizrika u'lazeh bizrika, לזה בשלשול ולזה בשלשול,
lazeh beshilshel u'lazeh beshilshel, also referred to as
לזה בקשה ולזה בקשה. lazeh bekasha u'lazeh bekasha.
Similarly, it's equally relevant to both of them and it's אסור asur
for both. If one it's easy and one it's hard, it goes
to the one it's easy. And the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel is, let's say they're competing for two different ways of
it being hard of access. One is בזריקה, bizrika, it's going up,
and the other is בשלשול beshilshel going down. And so שמואל Shmuel
says it's easier access by שלשול shilshel or presumably as we'll see
some of these cases are not necessarily bending down, like bending into
a ditch, but maybe lowering something down with a bucket or something
like that. That's easier access and therefore it goes to that one.
Although again, it is a little funny because as we pointed out
the height we're talking about of ten טפחים, tefachim, and ten טפחים
tefachim is perfect height to be using if it's above ground. I
mean, higher is an issue. But anyway. And רב Rav says no,
they're equally competing and therefore it's אסור. asur. Okay, and we're, so
the rest of today is going to try to be to prove
one position or the other between רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, if
to one it's accessible by going down and the other accessible by
going up, and it's equal you know and it's both of them
it's one it's deeper than ten, one it's higher than ten. Is
it are is it considered equal and אסור asur to both, or
is it considered connected to the one who has to who it's
who has to go down for it? That that's considered easier access.
So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. אי
הכי,
Ee
hachi, if that's true, meaning how it was explaining our משנה, mishna,
that the משנה mishna was talking about when it talked about a
mound in the courtyard, that it went to if it was high,
it went to the people of the מרפסת, mirpesset, of the patio,
of the walk-around. It said that
according to שמואל, Shmuel, why would, I'll just remind you, and here
I'm already missing a second marker yesterday. I'm missing one anyway.
One of them gave out on you.
No no no, I had two since then, I brought another. Anyway,
you've got here, you know, a מרפסת, mirpesset, a porch. Okay?
And here's your courtyard, חצר. chatzer. And
here are your, I don't know, I can't even draw maps, you
know, whatever, you know, this goes down or whatever, here are your
various, you know, homes in the courtyard.
What's underneath the מרפסת? mirpesset?
What?
It's okay. No, there's three there's homes that are built into the
wall, whatever. It doesn't matter. Anyway, and here you've got a mound,
so it says that if this is more than ten טפחים, tefachim,
okay, then it goes to the people of the
מרפסת. mirpesset. Okay, goes to that. So the גמרא Gemara says I
don't get it. This is should be a case of רב Rav
and שמואל. Shmuel. These people have to go up, these people have
to go down, and we're giving it to the people of the
מרפסת, mirpesset, right? Doesn't that prove that you give it to the
people who who have it in the down access, שמואל's Shmuel position?
And רב Rav says they're considered equal and nobody gets it. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no. The case is, we're not
talking about the people that live up here in the עלייה, aliyah,
okay, and then they would have to come out down to the
מרפסת. mirpesset. We're actually talking about the people that live in the
מרפסת mirpesset itself. And for them, this is less than ten טפחים.
tefachim. This is only nine טפחים. tefachim. It's very close. And that's
how רב Rav would explain why it goes to the people of
the מרפסת. mirpesset. But if it was more than ten for both,
or ten or more for both, it would be equal. So now
the גמרא Gemara is going to continue on that, let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אי הכי, ee hachi,
if that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, אימא סיפא, ema seifa,
let's look at the end of the משנה. mishna. פחות מכאן לחצר.
pahos mikan lachatzer.
If the mound is less than ten, it goes to the people
of the חצר. chatzer. אמאי? Amai? לזה בפתח ולזה בפתח הוא. lazeh
bepetah u'lazeh bepetah hu.
If it's less than ten, now I gave an example of nine,
but the גמרא Gemara was imagining maybe that it's even less, I
don't know, let's say that it's two אמות amos from these guys.
So it says how come if it's
less than ten, so let's say if it's nine, why does it
go to the people of the חצר? chatzer? If we're talking about
the people of the מרפסת, mirpesset, not people way up here in
the
עלייה, aliyah, so when it's lower than ten, it's totally related to
the חצר chatzer because it's always difficult for the people up here.
But if you're talking about the people right next to it, so
when it's... lower than ten it should be then it should be
equal access. So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says: אי הכי אימא סיפא
*I hakhi eima seifa*, פחות מכאן לחצר *pachos mikan lachatzer*. אמאי *Amai*?
Why's that true? וזה בפתח וזה בפתח *Vezeh bepesach vezeh bepesach*, which
is a way of saying it's equal easy access to both. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. מאי לחצר אף לחצר *Mai lachatzer af
lachatzer*. What we mean is if it's lower than ten then it's
connected even to the חצר chatzer. *chatzer*. It was always connected to
the מרפסת mirpesset, *mirpesset*, it was always within ten of the מרפסת
mirpesset *mirpesset*. If it's lower than ten from the ground, it's also
connected to the חצר chatzer *chatzer*, and because it's connected to both,
ושניהם אסורים *ushnayhem asurim*.
So it means, so if you have this more than ten, this
is the way רב Rav *Rav* reads it, if you have this
more than ten, you know, then it's only connected to the מרפסת
mirpesset. *mirpesset* because it's always much closer, it's a mound and it's
always much closer to the מרפסת mirpesset, *mirpesset*, okay? If it's less
than ten, then it's also connected to the חצר chatzer, *chatzer* and
therefore both become אסור assur *asur*, which is a little hard read
when it says it belongs to the חצר chatzer, *chatzer*, it means
that actually it's אסור assur *asur*. But that's the way the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara* is reading it according to רב Rav *Rav*. Okay. ושניהם
אסורים *ushnayhem asurim*. הכי נמי מסתברא *Hakhi nami mistabra*, that makes sense.
מדקתני סיפא *Mi de'katani seifa*, במה דברים אמורים *bameh devarim amurim* בסמוכה
*bis'mucha*, when is this true? If the mound is near the מרפסת
mirpesset *mirpesset*. אבל במופלגת *Aval bimupleget*, if the mound is away from
the מרפסת mirpesset, *mirpesset*, meaning, and the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* says, more
than four טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, אפילו גבוה י׳ טפחים tefachim. לחצר *afilu
gavoha yud tefachim lachatzer*.
So if you've got it that now the distance of this mound
here is more than four טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*, okay? So it's more
than four טפחים tfachim. *tefachim* here, so then it's always considered difficult
access to the מרפסת mirpesset *mirpesset*. No matter how close it is,
the fact that it's out there, right, it's not easy to get,
it's always difficult. So it says if it's מופלגת *mupleget* then it
always belongs to the חצר chatzer *chatzer*. Certain way that makes sense,
yeah, because it's too far away from them. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say I don't understand. If it's high, then
okay, it's difficult here that you have to bridge the gap, but
it's also difficult here that it's very high up. Why does the
חצר chatzer *chatzer* get preference just because it's far away? Alright? So
we're not making a distinction. It could be a hundred אמות *amot*
high and five טפחים tfachim *tefachim* away, right? Why does the fact
that as soon as this is more than four, it automatically goes
to the חצר chatzer, *chatzer* even if it's high? You know, a
simple scenario here is that it's equally difficult for both. So it
says, so it says, אבל במופלגת אפילו גבוה עשרה טפחים asara tfachim
לחצר *aval bimupleget afilu gavoha asara tefachim lachatzer*. מאי לחצר *Mai lachatzer*?
What does it mean that it goes to the חצר chatzer, *chatzer*?
אילימא לחצר ושרי *Ileima lachatzer veshari*, it only belongs to the חצר
chatzer. *chatzer* and therefore they can use it. אמאי *Amai*? Why is
that true? רשות דתרוייהו הוא *Reshut d'itravaihu hu*. It's connected to both
of them, meaning for both of them it's difficult access. Okay, so
it's equally difficult. אלא מאי לחצר אף לחצר ושניהם אסורים *Ela mai
lachatzer af lachatzer ushnayhem asurim*. So actually when the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
says when it's removed it's the חצר chatzer *chatzer*'s, it means it's
also the חצר chatzer. *chatzer*'s, not only the חצר chatzer *chatzer*'s, and
what that actually means is that it's אסור assur *asur* for both
of them. הכי נמי *Hakhi nami*, so here too, when we say
that if it is, when we say that if it's less than
ten, the חצר *chatzer* gets it, we don't mean just the חצר
*chatzer* gets it. We mean that if it's less than ten, since
it's always less than ten here, right? That's five or two, whatever
it is, it's always less than ten. So we don't mean it's
just the חצר *chatzer*'s. What do we mean? מאי לחצר אף לחצר
ושניהם אסורים שמע מינה *Mai lachatzer af lachatzer ushnayhem asurim shma mina*.
So that is a good read of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*. So
basically what we have is the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, just to sort
of recap, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says that if this mound, this
mound,
has, by, if it's higher than ten, goes to the מרפסת mirpesset
*mirpesset*, goes to the people, the, you know, the people on the
second story. So שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* basically reads it because it's a
preference to those that have access by going down rather than access
going up, and it's equally difficult for both, but we give preference
to the higher people. That's the way that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* reads
it. רב Rav *Rav* refuses that and he says if it's equally
difficult or equally easy, it's going to be equal and therefore אסור
assur *asur*. So why is there for the preference to the people
higher? Because for them it's in a situation that it's actually quite
close to the mound and it's always easy access. So he reads
the משנה *Mishnah* that it's always easy access for the people up
there. So then in situations where it's lower and more connected to
the חצר *chatzer*, or it's further away from the balcony and more
connected to the חצר *chatzer*, for him ultimately it's always equal in
terms of easy and difficult access for both sides and it would
always be אסור assur. *asur* for both. Okay, so, yes?
Are we always defining, it seems like we're defining the usage based
on its top. What about the slope? I mean, you know, maybe
the people in the חצר *chatzer* can use...
Alright, we'll get to that in a little bit about a well,
okay? It's a good point. We are assuming that that's the default,
that the standard use of it is the top. We'll talk about
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, not exactly your case of the slope, but a
case about other uses when we deal with a mound around a
well where you also use the bottom of the well.
But basically we have the debate of רב Rav *Rav* and שמואל
Shmuel *Shmuel*, where שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* says you prefer the people above,
and רב Rav *Rav* says they're equally competing for it and how
that plays out in the משנה *Mishnah* where רב Rav *Rav* reads
the statement that says לחצר *lachatzer* not to mean only to the
חצר *chatzer* but even to the חצר *chatzer*. חצר and it's אסור
assur. for both of them. תנן Tnan now we're going to keep
on going in our משנה. חוליית הבור והסלע שהן גבוהין עשרה למרפסת
פחות מכאן לחצר. Chuyas habor v'hasela shehen gevohan asara l'mirpesset pachot mikan
lachatzer.
So the first case is you have a rock that's ten high.
Again ten or more it goes to the מרפסת, mirpesset. lower it
goes to the חצר. That would play out exactly the way we
discussed before about the mound. And again רב Rav, is saying the
מרפסת mirpesset is low down and it has always within ten of
the מרפסת. mirpesset But now the problem we're going to focus on,
which is a new problem, it's not just a mound or a
rock, but we're going to focus on a well. So you've got
a well here.
Okay, okay, this is your underground here. You've got your well and
around the well you built up this you know this like wall
around the well, this mound around the well. You can sort of
see this is like a cut for you know whatever. Okay so
if this mound is higher than ten, okay same הלכה. halacha. If
it's greater than ten off of the ground, it goes to the
people up here. All right, so we'll make it higher so it
looks like the other picture. Okay so it goes to the people
up here. But now the גמרא Gemara going to have a problem
because according to רב Rav? there's no preference to the people of
the מרפסת, mirpesset right? שמואל Shmuel's always has the preference to them
because they only have to go down, these guys have to go
up.
They go up like what? Can they go up? I mean they're
going up and down right?
Right so these guys actually of the חצר who want to use
the well have to go both up and down. The guys up
here the מרפסת mirpeset just have to go down to use the
well. Okay if they want to use the top of it that's
different but they presumably might also want to use the well. Okay
so רב Rav, so שמואל Shmuel. says we always give preference to
the people of the מרפסת, they're going down, these guys are going
up. But רב Rav, says we don't give that preference. So the
only reason the מרפסת won in the earlier cases of the משנה
was because the distance to the top of the mound was less
than ten. And here the distance was more than ten and that's
the only reason. But the גמרא Gemara says that might be true
about using the mound, but if you want to actually not use
the top of the mound, you want actually lower in your bucket
and use the well, right? So then for these guys it's more
than ten and for these guys it's more than ten. So רב
Rav should say that in that case it should be אסור assur
to both of them. Now you could make a distinction and say
that these guys have to go up and down, these guys just
have to go down and that's different than the case that they
were talking about when it was just one direction. But that at
least is the גמרא Gemara question that if according to רב Rav
the reason we gave it to the מרפסת was that it was
less than ten, that in this case there's no reason that you
can't say that it's easy because even they have to get to
it by going down as well.
It's creating such a complicated scenario for people who are living in
the same area. Right. Some are permitted to do this, some are
permitted to do this. Right. It depends on the measurement on the
inches on the feet. Why would they do this?
I have to agree it's all
very interesting but in real life you see some people...
Well there has to be some ruling. Well look I could say
yeah I don't know the answer to it. I mean you're right
like as opposed to other areas which are intricate like I don't
know כשרות kashrut or whatever, this is more of a thing that's
given to the common person on a regular basis and it and
how do you imagine... and it changes. Right. Look if I have
no idea why what motivated... I mean one thing I could say
certainly is that all of these things make a greater push for
them to make an עירוב eiruv together, which we have been seeing
is a whole theme about creating that coherence that cohesiveness of community.
The other thing I'll say though is there needs to be rulings,
meaning if there's a case that these guys can't use this, this
can't be used by the guys up here and this can't be
used by the guys down here, so we're going to have to
give a ruling about things that are like mounds and that are
somewhere midpoint between the bottom and the top. So I mean I
don't know what system you would imagine that would be more simple,
but there needs to be a ruling about those issues. And we've
seen them.
First they have the general rule that an עירוב eiruv you make,
right? Right and we have seen in other areas where they will
make rulings so that people shouldn't get confused right and for מראית
עין maras ayin right.
You're right.
You're right. I mean one could imagine... I'm just saying there needs
to be a ruling. Could the rule have been a lot more
simple? Probably yes. I don't have an answer. So it's a good
point, yeah. So look I will also say and this is total
speculation but we have seen that הוצאה hotza'ah takes up a way
disproportionate amount, like it took up about you know half of מסכת
שבת, Masechet Shabbat, it's a little exaggeration but still a third of
מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat and it's a whole other מסכת עירובין Masechet
Eruvin devoted to it and it's the very opening of מסכת שבת
Masechet Shabbat and it's you know it's the one מלאכה melachah that
is called like מלאכה גרועה melachah gerua by the ראשונים Rishonim because
it's the one non-creative מלאכה melachah and part of that might be
it might be like a little bit of overcompensation like you know
because look we know here we know like fifty years ago,
seventy years ago people would
be שומר שבת shomer Shabbat Jews but. often not treated as seriously
as the others, this might be a way of giving it all
this greater weight. It also could be that it might have been
more disputed by the non-rabbinic circles, you know, about whether, you know,
by the צדוקים Tzedukim and so on. So that might have led
to a greater, you know, a greater giving much more attention and
weight to this. Yes.
In the case of the well, it would be, it would in
most cases, assume רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, so how could either party
be able to access use the well when...
what do you mean? They're both רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Right, so
why can't you go from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid if it's connected to your courtyard?
Because you're going because you're going into the court, you'd need to
make an עירוב eruv because it would be a separate רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid.
But that's the whole point. The whole point is the same mound
was just a mound. Yes, it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but
it might be these guys' רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, or it might
be these guys' רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. The whole point is that
it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid that's an extension of one of
the existing domains.
Well, existing to make it considered connected, right, but thank you for
clarifying is what you're actually saying is, no, this isn't some other
thing, this is an extension of my חצר, an extension of my
מרפסת. Okay, so that's going to be the גמרא's Gemara question now,
that according to רב, if the only reason you gave it to
the מרפסת was it was less than ten, in this case it's
more than ten.
Doesn't this explain let's say if there are other like water sources?
If you want, but if you want to use this. Let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this: הוי סלע ובור בשלשה
שהן גבוהין עשרה, למרפסת, פחות מיכן לחצר. havy sela uvor bishlosha shehen
gevohin asara, l'mirpesset, pachos mikan l'chatzer. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
so and the גמרא Gemara doesn't even have to like explain the
question, presumably it's self-evident what the question is. So I'm sorry, no.
The first question is that we assumed we assumed that מרפסת meant
the people
here in the עליה aliya way up here. So we want to
say why did they get preference according to רב? They clearly are
more than ten. So here's the same answer we gave at the
end of yesterday. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, what does it
mean למרפסת? l'mirpesset? לאו סמהדורין במרפסת. lav sam hadarin b'mirpesset.
It doesn't mean the people ממש mamash and the way up second
story for them it's for them it's they have no preference. We're
talking about the people right on the balcony, which it's closer to
them. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, תינח סלע, teinach sela,
I get that by the rock like we discussed by the mound.
It's closer to the people of the מרפסת and it's even less
than ten away from them. But בור מאי איכא למימר, bor mai
ika l'meimar, what do you do with the well case? Because even
if the beginning of the mound is within ten, but to get
to the bottom, you have to really go very deep and you
have to go much more than ten. So אמר רב יצחק בריה
דרב יהודה, Amar Rav Yitzchak breih d'Rav Yehuda, הכא בבור מלאה מים
עסקינן. hacha b'vor meleia mayim askinan.
Ah, it's a case where you don't have to go so deep,
that the pit is filled with water, okay, and therefore, now of
course I don't exactly get it because even if it's filled with
water up to the top of the pit, you might have to
assume that it's filled all the way up to the top of
here, you know, including the sort of surrounding stuff around it. So
therefore they actually don't have to go lower than ten. It's filled
all the way up to the top, so they don't have to
go lower than ten and you're back to the previous scenario. So
the גמרא Gemara says, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says: והא
חסרה, v'ha chasra,
how can you allow them to use it because right now it's
within ten. You'll start using it and then it'll be less than
ten... I mean more than ten, excuse me, and you know then
it'll become a problem. But it says, כיון דכי מליא שרי, keivan
d'ki malya shari,
since when it's full it's permissible, כי חסרה נמי שרי, ki chasra
nami shari, even when it's not full we'll allow... we'll assign it
to the guys above. So the גמרא Gemara says, אדרבה, aderaba, you
should say the opposite. כיון דכי חסרה אסירה, keivan d'ki chasra asira,
since it's going to be a problem when it's not full, כי
מליא נמי אסירה, ki malya nami asira, even when it's full it
should be considered a problem. And therefore since it's equally difficult for...
according to שמואל Shmuel this is no problem. You always prefer the
people that just have to go down, which is the people on
the top, rather people that have to go up, certainly if they
have to go up and down. But according to רב, if the
only reason you give it to the people above is because it's
within ten, so the גמרא Gemara says, it's not within ten getting
to the stuff in the well. אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye,
הכא בבור מלאה פירות עסקינן. hacha b'vor meleia peiros askinan.
Fine, it's not filled with water, it's filled with fruit. So it
really is like it becomes like a mound essentially. So the גמרא
Gemara says, right because you're not going down into the depth, it's
like the fruit is right there at the top. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והא חסרי, v'ha chasri,
same question, those fruit will go away. בטבלא. b'tivla. All right, we're
talking about fruit that's טבל. tevel. Fruit that you can't eat on
שבת, Shabbos, it hasn't had תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros taken. So effectively
nobody's using it. So effectively you're just using this as a mound.
This whole thing is filled with fruit, and this thing has turned
into now no longer a well but effectively a mound and you're
using the top of it, you're putting stuff on the fruit or
using the top of it. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. Why you need two cases? So the גמרא Gemara,
says, דיקא נמי, deika nami,
actually the גמרא Gemara says that seems like a good read of
the משנה, דקתני דומיא דסלע, d'katani dumya d'sela,
because that makes it just like the rock. Of course you would
say the opposite, that's so much like the rock that that's not
probably what the משנה's talking about.
According to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, it reads well. You give it to
the people here, or even the people up here, according to שמואל
*Shmuel*, because they only have to go down, and you always prefer
that to going up. According to רב *Rav*, you only give it
to them because it's within ten. So according to רב *Rav*, the
case is that this effectively is totally filled and is just a
variation on the סלע *sela*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, if
that's true, ולמה לי למתני בור ולמה לי למתני סלע *v'lama li
l'misni bor v'lama li l'misni sela*, why do I have to give
both cases? צריכא *tzricha*, you need both. דאי אשמעינן סלע דליכא למיגזר
*d'ee ashmi'inan sela d'leka l'migzar*, if you said by the rock you
give it to the people of the מרפסת *merpeset*, of the
balcony, of
whatever, the patio, then... what's a מרפסת *merpeset*? Porch, balcony,
whatever, anyway, whatever. Okay. Porches, porch, but a porch can also be
low, right? A מרפסת *merpeset* is up, so... balcony, whatever. Anyway,
מרפסת *merpeset*, balcony. Alright, fine. Anyway,
so if you had just said a rock, then I'd say fine,
a rock I get why it always goes to the people of
the balcony, דליכא למיגזר *d'leka l'migzar*, because you're never afraid that the
rock is going to get lower. Okay, I skipped a line, I'm
just trying to find where I am. דליכא למיגזר *d'leka l'migzar*. אבל
בור *aval bor*, but the well, even if it's filled, לגזור שמא
תתמלא פירות מתוקנים *ligzor shema titmalei peirot metukanim*, maybe we shouldn't let
the top guys use the well because sometimes it'll be filled with
fruit that will be fixed, meaning not be תרומה *trumah*, not be
טבל *tevel*, and that you'll be able to use, and that therefore,
and then when you use it, you'll take out the fruit and
you'll eventually be going lower than ten. צריכא *tzricha*, so it has
to tell me that no, right now if it's filled and it's
filled with stuff you can't remove, that's fine. Again, does not sound
at all that way from the משנה *Mishnah*. If it were that
special case and was trying to tell me something about that special
case, it should have said it. So the simple reading of the
משנה *Mishnah* is like שמואל *Shmuel*, that you give preference to the
people that are going down. But רב *Rav* says it's a special
case that it's totally filled and therefore it's again within ten of
the people of the second story.
Let me return back to my question. Let's say you had like
a much lower well that doesn't have this big mound, right? Then
wouldn't you say, okay, well this is a higher well, then you
may say the חצר *chatzer* has such easier access to a different
well and it's more likely that the, you know, as opposed to
a higher
well you'd get access to... No, no, it doesn't matter. Just because
we have one well, we also want the other well, and if
the other well is more connected to us, it should be ours
as well. You wouldn't say that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: תא שמע Ta shema, *ta shma*, come and hear.
אנשי חצר ואנשי עליה ששכחו ולא עירבו *anshei chatzer v'anshei aliyah sheshach'chu
v'lo eirvu*, same scenario, they forgot to make an עירוב eruv *eiruv*,
the top guys and the bottom guys. אנשי חצר משתמשים בעשרה תחתונים
ואנשי עליה משתמשים בעשרה עליונים *anshei chatzer mishtamshim b'asara tachtonim v'anshei aliyah
mishtamshim b'asara elyonim*. So what it says is let's erase our well.
Okay, these guys did not make an עירוב eruv, *eiruv*. Okay, this
is here your airspace. Okay, so the first ten טפחים *tefachim* of
the airspace, anything that's here goes to the חצר *chatzer*. The first
ten טפחים *tefachim* of the airspace going down, everything here goes to
these guys, right? Because this is considered easy access here and this
is easy access here. So presumably anything in this middle space, right?
Already this pen. Anything in this middle space is difficult access to
both and therefore presumably אסור assur. *assur*. That actually supports the position
of רב *Rav*, right? שמואל *Shmuel* says if it's difficult to both,
you give preference to the guy who's going down. Okay, but this
sounds
like the lower ten is to the חצר *chatzer*, the top ten
is to the מרפסת *merpeset*, and presumably the middle is to neither
of them, which is again a proof of רב *Rav*. Is that
clear? Yes, רב *Rav* says when they're up and down and it's
equally difficult, nobody gets it. שמואל *Shmuel* says you give it to
the top guy, and here actually we're giving it to no one.
So let's take a look. אנשי חצר ואנשי מרפסת *anshei chatzer v'anshei
merpeset*, אנשי חצר ואנשי עליה ששכחו ולא עירבו *anshei chatzer v'anshei aliyah
sheshach'chu v'lo eirvu*, אנשי חצר משתמשים בעשרה תחתונים *anshei chatzer mishtamshim b'asara
tachtonim*, the חצר *chatzer* people get the lower ten. אנשי עליה משתמשים
בעשרה עליונים *anshei aliyah mishtamshim b'asara elyonim*, the people of the second
story, not even the מרפסת *merpeset*, even higher, get the top ten.
כיצד *keitzad*, how is this true?
Exactly, it's all air.
Okay, what can I tell you. This is the היוצא *hayotzei*, you
can join Rifka's complaint about this being too complicated. זיז היוצא מן
הכותל *ziz hayotzei min hakotel*, if you have a protrusion coming out
of the wall, למטה מעשרה lemata me-asara, לחצר *lemata me'asara l'chatzer*, within
the ten of the ground it's the חצר *chatzer*. Now למעלה מעשרה
לעליה *lemala me'asara l'aliyah*, above ten to the people above. Now that's
not exactly what we said before. Before we said the top ten.
So for now we're going to read למעלה מעשרה *lemala me'asara* means
in the top ten, okay, to make it consistent with what we
said before. Bottom ten to the חצר *chatzer*, top ten to the
עליה *aliyah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הא דביני ביני *ha
d'beini beini*, the space that's neither the top ten or the bottom
ten, the space that's in the middle, אסור assur. *assur*, is forbidden.
So that's a proof to רב *Rav* that if it's equally difficult
top and bottom, you don't prefer the top, you actually give it
to, you actually say that it's equal and it's אסור assur. *assur*
to both. אמר רב נחמן, הכא בכותל תשסר עסקינן. hacha bekosel tish'asar
askinan. We're talking about a wall that's only 19.
זיז יוצא ממנו Ziz yotzei mimenu and that has that protrusion למטה
מעשרה, לזה בפתח ולזה בשלשול laze be-pesach ve-laze be-shilshul below 10, it's
easy access to one and hard to the other.
ולמעלה מעשרה u-lemala me-asara above 10 לזה בפתח ולזה בזריקה. laze be-pesach
ve-laze be-zrika. It's easy access to one and it's hard access by
going up. שלשול Shilshul is hard by going down. זריקה Zrika is
hard by going up.
What does that mean?
It means that, can I have your pen?
I don't know why my pens keep on
crapping out on me.
I use them too hard. No?
Okay, I'll borrow your book for it. All right, so what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is we're talking about a case that there's
no middle space, that there's no middle between the top 10 and
the bottom 10. The entire space is 19. Okay, now, and but
we'll only talk about this in whole- oh, thank you. The entire
space is 19. Thank you. So therefore, if the entire space is
19, okay, so this is here, this line is 10. Okay, so
from there to there is 10 and from here to here is
nine. Okay, so if it is,
if the bottom people get the lower 10 and the top people
get the top 10, right? The top 10 actually means- well, let's
not call it the top 10. So if it's within the bottom
10, if you have an object within the bottom 10, it's לזה
בפתח, laze be-pesach, to these guys it's easy access, and לזה בשלשול,
laze be-shilshul, to these guys it's difficult because these guys you'd have
to go more than 10. And that really, because you could imagine
that it would be right here and to these guys it would
be like 9.5, okay? But we're dealing in whole units. Imagine that
we're really 19 or really- imagine it's like that, okay, 9.99 or
whatever. So anything that is below 10 is within 10 of these
and it exceeds 10 for the people above. Is that clear? So
therefore, that's why it goes to these people. Anything that's above 10
is hard access to the people above because that's considered hard access,
more than 10 is hard access, and it's easy access to the
people- I mean, hard access to the people below and easy access
to the people above. So the basic answer of the גמרא Gemara
is we are not talking about that there is an actual gap
between the top 10 and the bottom 10. In that case according
to שמואל, you would give it by preference to the top because
you always prefer the top people over the bottom. What we're talking
about is a scenario where there's no gap and therefore if it's
less than 10, it's easy access to these and hard access to
those. More than 10,
it's easy access to the top and hard access to the people
below.
But what about the- what about the issue that at 10 it's
equal access to both?
Yeah, we're not talking about- well, no, but according to the גמרא,
Gemara by 10 it would still- actually once it hits 10, actually
it goes to the people above because the whole thing is 10
is already considered out of the range. So once it hits 10,
it's hard to this and it's easy to that because the whole
space is 19.99. So once it hits 10, it's within 10 of
the people above and it's 10 or more of the people below.
Wait, so if the thing is nine, then even though it's within
10-
even if this protrusion is at the ninth טפח, tefach, even though
it's within 10 of the top- it's not within 10 of the
top, it says it's at the- no,
this is until from this point to this point is 9.99, from
this point to this point is 10. So if it's exactly at
10, it's within 10 of the top and 10 or more of
the bottom. It goes to the top. Anything that's a little bit
below here makes it 10 or more to the people on top
and less
than 10- so it's really 19 טפחים high but you're saying 9.99?
No, no, no. The גמרא Gemara doesn't mean-
it means 10 and 19 but in that case- in that case,
then it would be different, then there would be times where it
might be considered competing and you would apply שמואל's rule. Okay, so
now let's continue. Okay,
fine.
So that explains that case where the simple sense was like רב,
but we explained it as a special case according to שמואל. תא
שמע, Ta shema, says the גמרא, Gemara come and hear, you see,
on one hand you could be happy that it's so difficult because
there's a lot less גמרא Gemara to each page. רש״י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos's, have a lot and these are big רש״י's Rashi's and
תוספות's, Tosafot not because they have problems from other סוגיא, sugya, but
because they're trying to figure out what the גמרא Gemara, is talking
about. All right, so תא שמע, okay. שתי גזוזטראות זו למעלה מזו,
Shte gazzustraot zu lemala mizu, so
you have two- you have right- you have- you have basically a
גזוזטרא gezustra was that you've got-
okay, here you've got a body of water. You're very lucky you
have some seafront property and your house looks over over a body
of water and you've got- okay,
or-
or no longer
within
your 10 טפח.
tefach. Okay, and there's your window, some apartment building, whatever. And you've
got like a little קפיצה kfitza coming out, okay. Now you might
want to throw some refuse off of that ledge, okay, into the
ocean or you might want to draw water from the ocean, okay.
So what the משנה later is going to say is if you
want to do that, you make a מחיצה mechitza either above or
below, like this, and then you imagine as if it extends down,
and then if you have a hole here, you can sort of
draw water going through like that. Okay, and because that's what we
would do. But we will now not yet talk about having made
the מחיצה, mechitza, you've just got your ledge. So what we have
though is we have two ledges and maybe they're it's an apartment
building, maybe they're different people living in each house, okay. You've got
your two ledges. Let's take a look. שתי גזוזטראות Shtei gezustra'ot זו
למעלה מזו, zu lemala mizu, one is higher, but they're not on
top of one another, they're not directly parallel, whatever, in the same
line.
עשו לעליונה ולא עשו לתחתונה, Asu laelyona velo asu latachtona, if you
make this
this this box for these people up here so they've got their
thing and now they can use, they can get their water like
that, okay. עשו לעליונה ולא עשו לתחתונה שתיהן אסורות עד שיערבו. Asu
laelyona velo asu latachtona shtehen asurot ad sheye'arvu. Now again, these are
owned by different people and they haven't made an עירוב eruv with
one another, so neither of them that they these guys cannot use
their well. Why? Because it's considered within access of these guys. We'll
talk about how distant they are. Okay, it's within access of these
guys, they haven't made an עירוב, eiruv, so although these guys did
everything right, these people are considered to have access here and it's
considered their well as well. Now that sounds a little bit bizarre,
because I mean my god, they made it. But imagine it's not
really different than the case we talked about about the מרפסת and
the חצר, where these people down here might have been the one
that dug the well, right, but if it's considered equal access to
both people then then it's אסור assur? to both of them. Right?
So this is a case, they dug the well, but because of
the way it's configured and it's considered equal access, it's אסור assur
to both of them. So the same is true here, it's my
well, but if it's considered equal access to me and I throw
something over or whatever, then I make it אסור. Now we'll talk
in a minute about how far I have to be and so
on, but let's take a look. Okay, yes.
How do they make this מחיצה? mechitza?
How do they make it before שבת? Shabbat?
How do they?
I don't know, you just get some planks of wood and you
nail them down or whatever.
Do they have to put something?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, yeah. Right, okay. Now now they are within
I should mention that they are within ארבעה טפחים, arba'a tfachim, okay.
It's less than ארבעה טפחים. arba'a tfachim. So remember like the case
here that the mound has to be, you know, within ארבעה טפחים.
arba'a tfachim. Remember when the mound to be considered connected, if you
remember that? So here too it's within ארבעה טפחים, arba'a tfachim, it's
considered like that mound and therefore it's connected and therefore I have
access. All
right, now. עשו לעליונה ולא עשו לתחתונה שתיהן אסורות עד שיערבו. Asu
laelyona velo asu latachtona shtehen asurot ad sheye'arvu. Now why is that
a problem? Or what does that prove?
So
basically these guys, their
access is
שלשול, shilshul, okay, meaning going down. Their access is going down. What?
Their access includes a going up
component, זריקה zrika plus שלשול, shilshul, plus going down. So and it
says they're considered equal. So according to רב it's fine, it's difficult
for both, I don't really give a preference and I don't say
two beats out one or whatever or one beats out two. Here
it's one degree difficulty, here it's two degrees difficulty, I don't care.
רב says if it's difficult for both, they're equal. But שמואל says
no, you always give preference, they only have to go down and
you always give preference to down rather than up, and even the
more so that they have to go both up and down. So
why according to שמואל don't you say these guys, it's their well,
not those guys? Okay, it's a good question. If you think about
it, like I said, this is really just a more complicated case
of this, right? It's within ארבע arba access, I can go up
and down, you have to go down, and why don't we just
give preference to them because they're only going down?
Do you need בית סאתים Beis Sasayim even if you're within
ארבעה
טפחים arba'a tfachim of the water, right? What? You need בית סאתים?
Beis Sasayim? No, because only it's the גזוזטרא gazzustra has to be
a it's because a גזוזטרא gazzustra is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
the גזוזטרא gazzustra itself is more than עשרה טפחים off the ground.
But let's not talk about that. So
אמר רבה בר אבין Amar Rava bar Avin בבואים בני תחתונה דרך
עליונה למלאות. Bevoa'im bnei tachtona derech elyona lemalaot. The case is, it's
a special case that it's not just it happens to be within
four and in theory, but actually what happened is is that there's
some type of an access, and the reality is is that they
actually don't just throw a bucket there, they actually walk over, and
they walk over and they use it like that. So in practice,
they actually the in practice, this space is used by both people
and they haven't made an
עירוב together. Okay, so finish then. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. And what's the חידוש? chidush? Let's
take a
look. אביי אמר כגון דקיימי בתוך עשרה דהדדי. Abaye amar kigon d'kaiman
betoch asara dehadadi. And אביי Abaye says, the case is is that
they're within ten. אביי Abaye says, no, no, no, אביי Abaye says,
you don't have to say there's a ladder, right? We've already said
that this גזוסטרא gezustra here is less, it's within four away, to
make it consider accessible, right? Like the mound has to be within
four. So this is like, this is 3.99. Now your question was
they have to do זריקה. zrika. They have to go up. He
says, no, 'cause the height difference between them is less than ten.
So
if the height difference is less than ten, it's not considered to
be זריקה zrika either. So what do they have to do? They
just have to do שלשול. shilshul. They just have to lower. What
do they have to do? Also just שלשול. shilshul. Okay, the fact
that they have to go a little bit across and a little
bit up, since the across is less than four and the up
is less than ten, that's irrelevant. Okay, and that's why אביי Abaye
says it's considered to be equal access to
both. One minute. Okay. אביי אמר כגון דקיימי בתוך עשרה דהדדי. Abaye
amar kigon d'kaiman betoch asara dehadadi. ולא מיבעיא קאמר. ve'lo mibaya ka'amar.
Now it gets to Michael's question. Why does it give this case,
what's it really trying to tell me? ולא מיבעיא קאמר. ve'lo mibaya
ka'amar. לא מיבעיא, lo mibaya, it goes without saying, עשו בתחתונה ולא
עשו בעליונה דאסירי. asu betachtona velo asu be'elyona de'asiri. It's obvious that
if the bottom one had it and not the top, that that
would be
אסור. Why? דכיון דבגו עשרה דהדדי קיימי, dekivan d'begov asara dehadadi kaiman,
they're both within ten. אסרו אהדדי, asru ahadadi, meaning here you would
look, the obvious case is the opposite. You know, same scenario, within
nine and within four, but let's say you had the well here.
Okay? So
then the, I'm going to erase the window 'cause the window part
is just confusing. Okay, so you had the well here. So he
says there, it's obvious that they're אסור both ways. Why? Because first
of all, that's less than ten, less than four, but not only
that, ממש mamash everybody here is doing the same direction. They're going
down and they're going down. So that's obvious that they're both rough,
that they're both basically equal and therefore it's
אסור. Okay, אסרו אהדדי. asru ahadadi. אלא אפילו עשו לעליונה ולא עשו
לתחתונה, ella afilu asu le'elyona velo asu letachtona, but even in the
case we started with, that you made it for the top
one. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitchach amina, כיון דלזה בנחת ולזה בקשה,
kivan d'leze benachas u'leze bekasha, so I would have said look, technically
when you did it the other way and you had it this
way, technically you could say these guys go down and these guys
also they don't really go higher than ten and they don't really
go more than four, so effectively they're just going down. But in
practice, these guys just have to lower a bucket down and these
guys have to throw it up and get it to go over
and down and this is a or whatever I have to throw
high whatever. So this is has an up component. So even though
it's not the ten up, which is the formal amount to define
it in a different category, in practice it's a lot harder for
these guys. And maybe we should just look at the practical, and
this is an important point. All along we really have not been
asking like, you know, if the real question was like if Rifka
was writing the rules, the rules would just be, look, just look
at each case and decide who has easier access. Forget all this
formal blah blah blah, right? But what we've been doing is we've
been sort of defining in the abstract easy and hard access. And
it's all been based on ten טפחים. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying now, forget, even if it's lower than ten טפחים, it's still
clearly harder for these guys than it is for these guys, so
it should be considered their well and not their well. Okay, practically
it's harder for one than the other. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אפילו עשו לעליונה ולא עשו לתחתונה, ella afilu asu le'elyona velo
asu letachtona, so even in that case. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitchach
amina, I would have thought, כיון דלזה בנחת ולזה בקשה, kivan d'leze
benachas u'leze bekasha, for the guys at the top one it's easy
and the guys at the bottom one it's difficult, even if it's
within ten and within four it's still
difficult. ליהוי לזה שתשמישו בנחת, lehoui leze shetashmishto benachas, give it to
the one who it's easier for, give it to the top guys.
קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, so this is teaching you, כיון דבגו
עשרה קיימי, kivan d'begov asara kaiman, since technically it's within ten, אסרי
אהדדי, asrin ahadadi, it makes it forbidden. And this גמרא is actually
a beautiful גמרא although it's caught up in this complicated detail, to
get at the heart of I think what we were talking before,
which is when we say equally easy, equally difficult, we don't just
mean assess the practicality. We define them based on very formal rules,
and the formal rules are higher than ten or lower than ten.
If for one guy it's a thousand high and for one guy
it's twelve high, they're considered the same, right? And if one guy,
and if this case it's within ten even though clearly it's more
difficult, it's considered the same. So that's exactly what the גמרא is
saying, that's a really nice חידוש. chidush. I mean, again, it makes
for a lot more rules and makes life a lot harder, you
know, a lot more. complicated, you know, but that’s the גמרא, it
likes formal rules. So what it’s saying is, we don’t give a
preference here because within ten is all considered to be effectively the
same, even if in practice it’s easier for one than the other,
and you could have said the reverse. Higher than ten, right, it
also is considered to be effectively the same, meaning we have different
size courtyards, and for me it’s, you know, 200 high and for
you it’s 10 high, we’re in the same category. We go by
formal rules, not by practical ones. Okay, and now the גמרא says
כי הא, ki ha, and this is the case that רש״י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot have a real hard time understanding exactly what it’s
talking about and how it’s relevant. But כי הא דאמר רב נחמן
אמר שמואל, ki ha d'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, גג הסמוך לרשות
הרבים, gag hasamuch l'reshut harabim, you have a roof near the רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. צריך סולם קבוע להתירה. tzarich sulam kavua l'hatira. You
need a fixed ladder to make it
permissible. סולם קבוע לגג. sulam kavua l'gag. סולם קבוע אין סולם עראי
לא. sulam kavua in sulam arai lo. Only a fixed ladder and
not a temporary one. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? לאו משום דכיון
דבתוך עשרה הדדי קיימי אתו הדדי. lav mishum d'keivan d'betoch asara hadadi
kaimei atu hadadi. It must be because they’re within ten. Now, that’s
a... I just in purpose read that without explaining it so you
could just see
how sort of opaque that is. Look, I’m going to prove to
you that ten is all that matters, because of this roof with
that you need a ladder, and so you see obviously the issue
is about being within ten. So, so what the heck is going
on? So, the here, the way that the basic explanation, I’ll try
to give one reason, one explanation that makes some degree of sense.
Okay, you’ve got your rooftop here. Okay, you’ve got the חצר here,
and the people in the חצר want to use the rooftop,
they want access to the rooftop. But on the other side you’ve
got a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, and you’ve got the people
here in the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Okay, it’s not higher, I’m
trying to show depth, whatever. Anyway, you’ve got the people here in
the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, and they potentially have access to the
rooftop. Okay, so is... can you call this rooftop, it’s the same
idea of competing for space, can you call this rooftop belonging to
the חצר, or does the fact that it’s open to the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, this isn’t even about making an עירוב, but if
it’s that it’s open to the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, then then
you can’t use the חצר, you can’t consider it part of the
רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. But aren’t these people going from רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid?
What? רשות הרבים reshut harabim to רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, aren’t they?
I’m sorry? Aren’t these people in רשות הרבים reshut harabim going to
רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? So they don’t have equal access, because that
would be אסור.
Yeah, but hold on, I mean רש״י Rashi says it’s within ten,
let me just double-check תוספות’s Tosafot. explanation for one minute. Hold on
one second.
Let me just check תוספות. Tosafot
Right, it’s within ten. You’re right, yeah, it’s within ten, and the
whole and that’s why it’s considered accessible. So it’s a very small
building. I mean, I don’t know again, it’s so funny all of
these discussions are ten טפחים. What type of houses are we talking
about?
You know, anyway, a doghouse.
A doghouse! Anyway, what? The Hobbit. The Hobbit!
Anyway, so this whole lovely building is nine. So they both have
equal access. Okay,
so it says here, I’m just going to read you the simple
way of reading this, which is according to רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
It says if you make a סולם קבוע, sulam kavua, you fix
a ladder here, then it clearly belongs to the חצר. Okay, and
therefore you’re okay, you can use the roof. If however this ladder
is a temporary one, okay, then there’s nothing structurally, then when you
look, access it structurally, there’s nothing structurally that makes this more the
חצר’s than the רשות הרבים reshut harabim and therefore it’s אסור. What
does that prove? So the גמרא says, but why is it אסור?
Because why don’t we just say that in practice, you know, hold
on, let me just check תוספות one more second.
Right, meaning the גמרא says, I get, I get that if you
don’t have a fixed ladder, I get that structurally it’s equally connected
to both and it’s within ten טפחים of both. But even if
this ladder is temporary, right, even if it’s here, we’ll make
a, we’ll make a stepladder, okay. I don’t know how to draw
a stepladder. Anyway, whatever. Even if this ladder is a temporary one
and a movable one, if I was asking a practical question, not
a formal question, then practically speaking, who has easier access? The people
of the חצר. So and even so, we are going to say
it’s אסור unless you have the fixed ladder. Why? So you see
we go by the formal rule that if it’s less than ten,
I don’t care about practically it being easier for one or easier
for the other. If they’re both less than ten or they’re both
more than ten, I don’t ask practical questions, I put them in
the same category. Okay, and so again, it’s a complicated case but
according to רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, that’s the basic point: that if
it’s low, that even though in practice, even with a temporary ladder,
it’s much easier for the חצר people than the רשות הרבים reshut
harabim people. Since in terms of the formal rules they're the same,
it's going to be אסור *assur* both ways. Let's move on. Okay.
מתקיף לה *maskif lah* רב פפא *Rav Papa*.
So Rav Papa said, how do you know that that's because it's
practical—that it's formal? Maybe it's easy for the רשות הרבים *reshus harabim*
people as well. ודילמא כרשות הרבים מקטפי עליה בקומסא וסודרא *v'dilma k'reshus
harabim mekatefi aleih b'kumsa v'sudra*. So maybe that is, you know, so
maybe maybe the the the the people of the רשות הרבים *reshus
harabim*, you know, if it's within ten, maybe they put things on
it, you know, maybe they put their hats on it and their
sacks on it. Right, למכתפי *l'michtafei*.
So basically he says that that doesn't prove anything. Just because these
guys have a step ladder doesn't prove that it's so much easier
for these guys than it is for these guys. So in your
proof of formal versus practical, you haven't proved so much. But nevertheless,
even though we haven't proved it, that's basically the position of the
גמרא *Gemara* which has been the position all along. It's all been
basically defined by the formal question of within ten or higher than
ten, and not by assessing case by case. Again, if Rifka were
writing the rules, which would be hard to sort of say, you
know, look up an exact formula, but basically say, yeah, just go
figure out, who who is it easier for, right? But again, I'm
sort of saying this, Rifka, not to focus on you, but to
say that, you know, that in a way it's a lot easier
and it's a lot more commonsensical and you don't need a million
rules, but what the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't like about it is is
that it's subjective. It and and the גמרא *Gemara* wants to have
a handle on things and be able to have an exact answer
and a precise rule, like any legal system wants there to be
very, you know, precise laws. And that leads to all of this
degree of complication, and but then also you have the irony that
even if it really is easier for one than the other, if
in the same formal category, we're going to treat them as the
same. Okay, more of this fun stuff on Monday.